<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Chinese historical great man</string>
    <string name="bt_return">return</string>
    <string-array name="name">
        <item>Cai Lun</item>
        <item>Deng Xiaoping </item>
        <item>confucius</item>
        <item> Laozi</item>
        <item>CheLIu</item>
        <item>Mao Zedong</item>
        <item> Mencius </item>
        <item>QinShihuang</item>
        <item>Sima Qian</item>
        <item>JianYang</item>
        <item>ZhuXi</item>
    </string-array>
<string-array name="details">
    <item>Cai Lun (-121)
Dongyang Hunan Shuyang County people. The word is Zhongzheng, and the birth year is unknown. In the last years of the Ming Emperor, he entered the palace to fill the eunuch, and the middle calendar was Xiao Huangmen. When he was in the emperor\'s time, he stayed in the middle of politics. He used to be the governor of the court\'s royal utensils.
In the past, people used  or bamboo and wood to write. "It\'s expensive and simple, it\'s not convenient for people." When it came to the Western Han Dynasty, a kind of original paper appeared. When people rinse the silk thread, they often reveal a thin layer of floc on the banquet, which can be written, which is called wadding. When floating, there is a similar discovery, called hemp paper. This kind of original paper is neither commonly used nor small in number, and it is small, unsquare, and inconvenient to use.
Cai Lun was inspired by the time of the party, and he was organized to work as a craftsman and began to develop paper. Drawing on the experience of the predecessors, on the raw materials, we think of numbness, rags, old fish nets and bark from the numbness; in the production method, the raw materials are crushed, and then suspended and copied. The use of a single raw material began, and then several raw materials were mixed together to become a variety of raw materials, and the new method of papermaking was implemented. The first year of Yuanxing (105) was successful, used for writing, and gradually replaced enamel, bamboo and bamboo and original paper. In the first year of Emperor\'s Yuan Dynasty (114), it was sealed as Long Tinghou and 300 restaurants. This kind of paper is called "Cai Lun Paper". Later generations also passed Cai Lun as the inventor of papermaking in China.
First, in the time of the Emperor Zhang, Cai Lun was instructed by the Queen of Dou, and Luo Zhi was guilty of murder. In the second year of Yongning (121), in the March of the Tang Dynasty, Empress Dowager died, and Andi was pro-government and pursued his guilt.</item>
        <item>Deng Xiaoping (1904-1997) Great Marxist, proletarian revolutionary, politician, strategist, diplomat, one of the main leaders of the Communist Party of China, the Chinese People\'s Liberation Army, and the People\'s Republic of China, China\'s socialist reform, opening up, and modernization The chief designer, the founder of Deng Xiaoping Theory.
He was born in Fuling County, Ji\'an Prefecture, Jiangxi Province (now Ji\'an County, Ji\'an City, Jiangxi Province). He was born on August 22, 1904 in Paifang Village, Xiexing Township, Guang\'an County, Sichuan Province. Formerly known as Deng Xiansheng, the scientific name Deng Xixian. At the age of 5, he went to school in private school. In 1910, he entered the primary school of Xingxiang Township. In 1915, he entered high school and studied in 1918. After graduating from high school in 1918, he was admitted to Guang\'an Middle School. In the autumn of 1919, he was admitted to the Chongqing Work-study School for Study in France. In October 1920, he went to France to work and study in the Bayer Men\'s High School in Normandy. In 1922, he joined the European Communist Youth League Youth League branch. In 1924, he was elected as a member of the Secretariat of the Communist Youth League Executive Committee and was transferred to the Communist Party of China. At the beginning of 1926, he went to the Soviet Union to study at Zhongshan University in Moscow.</item>
        <item>Confucius (551 BC - 479 BC), Mingqiu, Zizhong, Lu Guochang Pingyi (now southeast of Qufu, Shandong). The thinkers, educators and politicians of the late Spring and Autumn Period, the founders of the Confucian school, are among the most influential figures in Chinese history and culture. They also have great influence in the world, especially in Southeast Asian countries, and are one of the world\'s cultural celebrities.
The ancestor of Confucius was the brother of the late Yin, the prince of the king, and the tribute to the Shang Dynasty. The father of the Sixth ancestors, Kong Jia, began with Kong as the surname. The five-year-old Zumu Jinfu took refuge to Lu, and later settled in Lu Guofan. The uncle, Liang Shu, was a warrior, and he was brave enough to smell the princes. In his later years, he married the Yan’s woman and gave birth to Confucius.
Confucius often used Chen Qidou and set the courtesy as a play. At the age of 3, he lost his father and was taught to be married to the sage. At the age of fifteen, he is determined to study. When I was young, I used to be a small officer who administers a granary and grazes. According to legend, he once asked the rites to learn from the old, learn to be happy, and learn to play in the teacher. At the age of 34, Emperor Lu of Meng Luzi and Meng Gong of Nangong came to the school. Since then, Confucius began to teach.</item>
        <item>The old man, surnamed Li Ming Er, the word Bo Yang, is the nickname, in the Spring and Autumn Period, the Chu State Bitter County (now the eastern part of Luyi County, Henan Province), the birth and death years are unknown. He used to be the history of the Zhou Dynasty\'s Guardian\'s House, and later was the history of the column. He was familiar with the changes of the ancient and the modern. In his later years, he lived in Pei, and he taught the disciples, and he talked about morality. After the West entered Guanzhong, the guest died in Qin.
After entering the Warring States, his quotations spread to Zhejiang and Guangxi, and finally finished by the Yuanyuan, becoming the "Tian Tao" and the next chapter, the present "Laozi." In Lao Tzu\'s book, the book of the universe is regarded as "Tao" or "Pak", sometimes called "None." The Tao is the mother force that creates everything, surpasses the absolute existence of time and space, the spiritual entity that can never be perceived, and the only way to take it is purely abstract "natural". This "mysterious and mysterious" way is always in accordance with the laws of nature, where it circulates, "week and not swearing." Only by closing the door and closing the door, "still watching the mysterious view", that is, "with Xuan Guan Xuan", can only understand. The so-called "do not leave the house, know the world", "it is far from the far-reaching, knowing that it is less." Starting from this, "Laozi" put forward the proposition of "the movement of the anti-doer", realizing that everything is in the opposite of the positive and negative aspects, they are interdependent and naturally transform each other, "it is amazing, good complex For the demon, "the blame for the blessings, the blessings of the blessings", "there is a benefit", "nothing to use".</item>
        <item>Liu Che, Han Wudi Liu Che (July 14, 156 BC - March 29, BC), the seventh emperor of the Western Han Dynasty, outstanding politician, strategist, poet.
At the age of sixteen, Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty enthroned the emperor. Adopting the advice of the father-in-law, enacting a decree, resolving the kingdom\'s forces, and bringing the salt iron and coining rights back to the center. Culturally, Dong Zhongshu’s suggestion was adopted, “stopping 100 schools and honoring Confucianism alone”, ending the situation of “different teachers, different people, and 100 families” since the pre-Qin period. During the Hanwu Emperor\'s reign, the country was far-reaching, the country was far-reaching, the East and North Korea, the South swallowed the Baiyue, the Western Expedition Dawan, and the North Xiongnu, laid the basic scope of the Han Dynasty, created the situation of the Hanwu flourishing world, and opened up the Silk Road and established The year number, the promulgation of the Taichu calendar, and the Xingtai school also have far-reaching effects.
Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty had made achievements in various fields, but in the late period of the reign of the army, the martial arts were caused by the martial arts, which left a negative evaluation. In the four years of Zheng Zheng (89 BC), Emperor Wu of Han Dynasty sinned. In the second year of the Yuan Dynasty (87 BC), Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty collapsed in the Wuyi Palace, at the age of 70, nicknamed Xiaowu Emperor, the temple number Shizong, buried in Maoling.</item>
        <item>Mao Zedong, Mao Zedong (December 26, 1893 - September 9, 1976), the word Run (original for Zhizhi, later changed to Runzhi), pen name. Hunan Xiangtan people. The leader of the Chinese people, Marxists, great proletarian revolutionaries, strategists and theorists, the main founders and leaders of the Communist Party of China, the Chinese People\'s Liberation Army and the People\'s Republic of China, poets and calligraphers. From 1949 to 1976, Mao Zedong served as the highest leader of the People\'s Republic of China. His contribution to the development of Marxism-Leninism, military theory, and his theoretical contribution to the Communist Party was called Mao Zedong Thought. Because Mao Zedong’s main duties were almost entirely called the chairman, he was also known as “the Chairman Mao”. Mao Zedong is regarded as one of the most important figures in the history of the modern world. Time magazine also named him one of the 100 most influential people in the 20th century.</item>
        <item>Mencius, Mencius (about 372 BC - 289 BC), a thinker, politician, educator of the Warring States Period, a representative of the Confucian Simmons School; Ming Hao, Zi Zi, Lu Guozou (now southeast of Zou County, Shandong Province) people. He is considered to be the successor of Confucius, and is known as the "Asian St."
According to legend, Mencius is a descendant of Meng Sunshi, a nobleman of the Lu nationality. He died in his childhood, his family was poor, and he was a student of Zi Si. After the completion of the course, he lobbied the princes as a priest and attempted to promote his own political ideas. He successively went to Liang (Wei), Qi, Song, and Teng. Although he was once regarded as a guest, he was not seen. In his later years, he retired from lectures and, along with his students, "prefaced "Poetry" and "Book", describing the meaning of Zhong Ni, and making "The Mencius". He stood in the Confucian position and succeeded in developing Confucius\'s thoughts and proposed a complete set of ideology, which had a great impact on later generations.
The highest category of Mencius\'s philosophy is heaven. He inherits Confucius\'s destiny thoughts, removes the meaning of the remaining personality gods, and imagines the heavens as spiritual entities with moral attributes. He said: "Cheng, the way of heaven is also." Mencius defined the moral concept of sincerity as the essential attribute of heaven, and believed that heaven is the origin of the moral concept inherent in human nature. Mencius is all due to the role of heaven. Therefore, he advocated "Lotte, fear of heaven, and heaven" and obediently accepted the arrangement of the heavens. His philosophical thinking has the nature of objective idealism.
Mencius believes that heaven and man are connected. Heaven is the master of all things. Everything about personnel, whether it is political system, moral principle, social and historical development, or personal poverty, is determined by heaven. People, not only goodness comes from talent, but also the thinking function of the human heart is also given by heaven. This kind of thought of unity between man and nature is concentrated in the following three philosophical propositions: "The one who does his heart, knows his nature. Knows his nature, then knows the heavens"; "everything is prepared for me. Sincerely, Le Mo Dawei"; "It is the sincere person, the way of heaven is also; the person who believes in sincerity, the way of man."</item>
        <item>Qin Shihuang, Qin Shihuang (pre-259-210), surname (one said Zhao surname), famous government, son of Qinzhuang, the outstanding politician, military strategist and commander in Chinese history.
Qin Shihuang was born in Zhao Guozhen in the forty-eighth year of Qin Zhaowang. He was born by Qinzhuang and Lu Buwei, so some people said that Qin Shihuang was the son of Lu Buwei. After birth, surnamed Zhao. In 247 BC, Zhuang Yu died, and Zheng Zheng was the throne of Qin, at the age of 13. Lu Guowei of the country has mastered the real power.
In 238 BC, the 22-year-old Qin Wangzheng was crowned in politics. In this year, the eunuchs launched the court coup, and Qin Shihuang sent Chang Pingjun and Chang Wenjun to lead the troops to encircle the long-term slogan, and offered a reward: "There is a birth, a million, and a killing, 500,000." Shi Ji·Qin Shihuang\'s book”). The insurgents will be wiped out. In the second year, he also took the drug-stricken incident and removed the position of Lu Buwei, the "second father", and took back the power of the political power into his own hands. He also listened to Li Si\'s argument, continued to reuse the guest, set the strategy of combining Jin Yuli and the attack of force, and speeded up the pace of war in the six countries.</item>
        <item>Si Maqian, Sima Qian (before 145-87 years ago), the word is long, Xihan Xiyang (now Hancheng of Shaanxi, one said Shanxi Hejin), the great historian, thinker and writer of the Western Han Dynasty, with "Historical Records" Also known as "Tai Shi Gong Ji", he recorded the history of the Yellow Emperor from the ancient Chinese legend, down to the four years of Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty (100 BC), a total of more than 3,000 years of history.
Sima Qian (145 BC - 87 BC), with his history of "taking the opportunity of the heavens and the earth, changing the ancient and modern times, becoming a family", made "Historical Records" the first general history of Chinese history, and had a great influence on later generations. Huge, Lu Xun was praised as "the singer of the historian, no rhyme." Sima Qian only wrote "Historical Records" in his life, and his father Sima Tan was a Tai Shiling (equivalent to the current position of the National Library Director). In the early years, Sima Qian lived in poverty in his hometown. In the sixth year of Jianyuan, after the death of Emperor Dou, the Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty ousted the old man, the name of the prison, and the words of the hundred families, and re-launched the Confucianism. This is the famous "dismissal of 100 families, and only respects Confucianism." In the second year of Emperor Wu of the Han Dynasty, Sima Qian moved to Chang\'an from Xiayang [Nian "Fake"], and then moved to Beijing with his family. He studied "Shang Shu" from Kong Anguo and "Spring and Autumn" from Dong Zhongshu. Then he succeeded his father as a history. In 104 BC, Sima Qian officially wrote "Tai Shi Gong Shu" while presiding over the revision of the calendar. In the second year of Tianhan (99 BC), he pleaded for Li Ling, who surrendered the Huns, because of the "Li Ling incident". Therefore, he angered Han Wudi and believed that he was defending Li Ling and was sentenced to death. In the prison, Sima moved to work hard, self-improvement, endured the pain that very humans can endure, and continued to write "Historical Records." After Sima Qian was released from prison, he was appointed as a librarian, continued to write an indignation, and finally completed the "Historical Records" in 91 BC. In 87 BC, Sima Qian passed away at the age of 56. As for the cause of death of Sima Qian, because the historical materials are not clearly recorded, it is still an unsolved mystery.</item>
        <item>Yang Jian, Yang Jian (541-604), namely Emperor Wendi, Xiaoming Na Luoyan, Hongnong Huayin (now Huayin City, Shaanxi Province). The founder of the dynasty, a famous politician in the history of our country.
Yang Jian was born in a famous family. According to legend, he is the fourteenth generation grandson of the Western Han Dynasty Tai Yang. His father, Yang Zhong, was one of the famous artists of the Northern Zhou Dynasty. He accompanied Yu Wentai in the Kansai uprising in his early years. Give the name Pu Liuru. He has made great contributions to the pillar country, Da Sikong, and Guo Guogong. Yang Jian, 14 years old, served as Jing Zhao Yin Cao. At the age of 15, he was given a regular ride by the father, a general rider, and a three division of Yitong. At the age of 16, he moved to the generals of the squadron and Jiakai. At the time of Emperor Zhou Ming, he served as the right small Gongbo and Jinfeng Daxing County. At the time of Emperor Zhou Wu, he was left to the small palace, and he was enlisted in the generals. Wu Di hired Yang Jian’s eldest daughter as the Crown Prince. Since then, Yang Jianyi has been favored. In the fourth year of Jiande in the Northern Zhou Dynasty (575), Yang Jian led the 30,000-water army to attack Beiqi. The following year, along with the Emperor Wudi, he entered the pillar country and became the general manager of Dingzhou (now Ding County, Hebei Province), and soon changed to the general manager of Zhangzhou (now Anhui Huaiyu). In the seventh year of Jiande (579), Zhou Xuandi was in the throne, and Yang Jian’s eldest daughter was sealed as a queen. Yang Jian worshipped Shangzhuguo and Sima. In the early years of the elephant, he served as a big shackle and a right sergeant.
In the second year of the Northern Zhou Dynasty elephant (580), Zhou Jingdi, who is only 8 years old, succeeded to the throne. Yang Jian, the prime minister’s father, was in charge of politics and took control of the supreme military and political power in the Northern Zhou Dynasty. At that time, the general manager of Xiangzhou (now Anyang, Henan) was dissatisfied with Yang Jian’s dictatorship, and the joint governor of Yizhou (now Hubei Anlu), Sima Xiaoyan, successively started to fight against Yang. Yang Jian was on the post of Guo Wei Xiaokuan, who was cruel to the shackles and calmed down the rebellion. In the February of the Northern Dynasties (581), Yang Jian overthrew Zhou Jingdi, and became the emperor himself. The Dingguo was a shackle, and the Yuan Dynasty was changed to the emperor. Opened a new page in history.</item>
        <item>Zhu Xi, Zhu Xi, the character Yuan Wei, later changed Zhong Zhong, No. 晦庵, also known as Ziyang, Jiangxi Wuyuan people, was born in Yuxi, Fujian. The father Zhu Song was appointed as the director of Youxi County in Song Xuanhe\'s five years (1123). On the fifteenth day of Jianyan four years (1130), Zhu Xi was born. Zhu Xi was smart and eager to learn at school. He was 7 years old and moved to Jianzhou with his parents (now Fujian Jianye). At the age of 14, he followed his father\'s dying and went to Hu Xian and Liu Yuzhi, friends of Chong\'an County. Hu, Liu Shi, Zhu Xi, such as Zi Zi, arranged life, and enthusiastic teaching. Liu Yuzhi also married his daughter to Zhu Xi.
In the 18th year of Shaoxing (1148), Zhu Xi Deng Jinshi. In the 21st year of Shaoxing (1151), he served as the main book of Tongan County in Quanzhou, where he often told the students and the students to talk about the sages. He also advocated the construction of the Jingge, collecting books for reading; in the aftermath of the business, exploring Buddha, old and various philosophical thoughts. After three years of full-time, he returned to Chong\'an Wuyi Mountain, built Zhongshan Hall, and lectured on his work. He walked to Yanping and asked his father, Li Wei, for advice. In the 30 years of Shaoxing (1160), Zhu Xi met with Li Wei for the third time and was accepted as a student by Li Wei. Zhu Xi’s “Escape from Zen to Confucianism” is directly inspired by Li Wei. Zhu Xi was instructed and influenced by Li Wei, inheriting the orthodoxy of "Luo Xue" and laid the foundation of science.
In the first year of Longxing (1163), Song Xiaozong pleaded with the opinions of all subjects. Zhu Xi’s chapter on narrative narrates the negligence of governance. He believes that “the study of the emperor must first learn from the things, and change the things of the great husbands, so that the righteousness is preserved, and the micro-photographs are vivid, and the natural meaning is sincere, and it can be done in the world.” It is intended to use politics to promote politics. In November of the following year, Zhu Xi and Xiao Zong played against the arched temple, and believed that Song and Jin had no share of the enemy, and advocated anti-gold, opposition and discussion.
In the three years of the main road (1167), Zhu Xiying, at the invitation of the Changsha Yuelu Academy, went to lectures and continued for more than two months to open the first session of the college. In the seven years of the main road (1171), due to the mother-in-law\'s funeral, I went back to my hometown. By the way, I visited the old site of my father\'s office, and kissed the book "Wei Zhai\'s old rule". In the nine years of the main road (1173), Youxi County re-educated the school, and Zhu Xi wrote "Re-repairing the Temple of Youxi Temple", the title book "Ming Lun Tang", and the system was hung in the main hall of Xuegong. Since then, the Temple of Heaven has been shackled and hung.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="photo">
        <item>@drawable/cailun</item>
        <item>@drawable/dengxiaoping</item>
        <item>@drawable/kongzi</item>
        <item>@drawable/laozi</item>
        <item>@drawable/liuche</item>
        <item>@drawable/maozedong</item>
        <item>@drawable/mengzi</item>
        <item>@drawable/qinshihuang</item>
        <item>@drawable/simaqian</item>
        <item>@drawable/yangjian</item>
        <item>@drawable/zhuxi</item>
    </string-array>
    <string name="skip_ad">SKIP</string>
</resources>
